Guide to the Darlington Family Papers, 1753-1921 DAR.1925.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Edith Dennison Darlington Ammon Papers, 1881-1882, 1908-1919; VII.
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, On the Nile, January 31, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Cairo, March 2 and 5, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Paris, May 3 and 7, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Paris, May 14, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, May 19-21, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, May 23, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, May 26, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, May 28, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - St. Louis World's Fair Souvenir booklets, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Article in the Pittsburgh Bulletin, June 1911 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Thomas P. Roberts to Edith Darlington Ammon, August 18, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Financial papers, January 6, 1908- June 16, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Sydney Liggett to Edith Darlington Ammon, March 16, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Samuel A. Ammon to Mrs. Mary Echler, May 20, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Ground leases (copy 1), April 1, 1913- April 1, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Ground leases (copy 2), April 1, 1918- April 1, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Photographs of the Greenhouse at Guyasuta, undated (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Watercolors of Flowers, undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - DAR Insignia, Allegheny Chapter, undated (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Pittsburgh Musical Society, 1897-1899 (Box 5a, Volume 54)
    Scrapbook compiled by Edith Darlington who wrote to a friend on January 8, 1914, this is "a book I kept during the active life of our musical society."
- Family Papers, 1826-1914; VIII.
  This diverse group of materials has been divided into three subseries. Subseries 1 contains photographs and ephemera collected or created by the Darlington family during their travels. Subseries 2 contains a few letters to extended family members and genealogical information about the Darlingtons. Subseries 3 documents Darlington properties, particularly the house at Guyasuta. Subseries 4 contains the papers of the Hemphill family, who were good friends of the Darlingtons.
  - Photographs and Ephemera, 1.
    The Darlington family collected souvenirs during their travels, including: a printed booklet from Washington, D.C.; souvenir cabinet cards of Florida locations such as Jacksonville, Silver Springs, Palatka, Leesburg, St Augustine, Daytona Beach, the Ocklawaha River, and Lake Worth; photographs of St. Michael's church in Charleston; and photographs of the basalt structures at the Giant's Causeway in North Ireland. Photographs of the Darlingtons during their travels include an image of Mary Carson Darlington and Edith Darlington with friends taken at Pikes Peak, Colorado, a photograph of Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington with her three children in front of Kenilworth castle, Warwickshire, England, and images from a Darlington family trip to Barcelona Harbor on Lake Erie in Pennsylvania.
    Additional photographs include: Hillborn Darlington; an unknown woman who could be Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington; and a photograph taken by O'Hara Darlington of his sisters with their friend Lilia. In addition to these photographs, a children's book includes the childhood signatures of O'Hara Darlington, Mary Carson Darlington and Edith Darlington on the front end leaf, and a number of unsigned water colors and sketches of natural scenes, likely done by Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington or her daughter, Mary Carson Darlington. For more information, please refer to Box 25, which may contain related oversized materials.
    - Washington, D.C., Souvenir booklet, 1884 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Florida color postcards, 1884 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Photographs from Florida trip, 1884 (Box 9, Folder 3-13)
    - Photograph on Pikes Peak, September 3, 1892 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Photographs from Barcelona Harbor, 1897 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Darlington Family Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - St. Michael's Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Photograph of Mary Carson, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Photograph Warwickshire, England, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Panoramic illustration of Victoria, British Columbia, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - The Adventures of a Bear, and a Great Bear Too, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Northern Ireland photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Trip to Honda, 1884 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Water colors and sketches, undated (Box 9, Folder 24-27)
    - Framed photographs, undated (Box 28, Item 1-3)
      - James O'Hara (portrait), 1.
      - William M. Darlington (portrait), 2.
      - Mary O'Hara Darlington (shown painting in greenhouse at Guyasuta), 3.
  - Extended Family Papers and Genealogical Materials, 2.
    This subseries contains genealogical materials documenting the Darlingtons, O'Haras and McCulloughs, including the Darlington family coat of arms. The subseries also includes correspondence from Darlingtons not represented by an independent series of materials, including the Third Earl of Darlington, Samuel Darlington and J. Darlington.
    - J. Darlington to Jacob Burnett, July 31, 1799 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Letter written by the Third Earl of Darlington, July 20, 1826 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Darlington Genealogical Papers, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Birth and Death Date Listings for the McCulloughs, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - William Wilkins to Samuel Darlington, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Darlington Coat of Arms, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Genealogy of the Darlington Family, 1900 (Box 10, Volume 51)
  - Family Properties, 3.
    The items listed below document the layout and dimensions of the Guyasuta mansion and surrounding property, including floor plans and gas pipe diagrams. Photographs show an additional Darlington property at Marshall Avenue and Brighton Road in Allegheny City. A land lease for property owned by Samuel Darlington and a list of properties sold on behalf of Jane McCullough are also present. For more information, please refer to Box 25, which contains oversized materials.
    - Guyasuta Road map, September 30, 1890 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Drawing of Guyasuta and environs, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Rooms at Guyasuta, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Guyasuta Floor Plan, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Gas Pipes, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Land Lease for Samuel Darlington, January 1, 1828 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Real Estate sold on behalf of Jane McCullough, November 17, 1830-August 13, 1831 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Hemphill Family Papers, 4.
    The Hemphills were close friends of the Darlington family. Collected here are a small number of family letters, including an 1861 letter from a Union soldier at Fort Lyon, and an 1886 letter describing a grandfather's tales about "bloody murders" at the hands of neighboring Indians along the Youghiogheny River. A handwritten Hemphill family tree is present, as are commemorative buttons and badges representing the National Encampment in Syracuse, New York, in September 1900; the 8th Annual Convention of the National Rivers and Harbors Congress; the 1900 Democratic National Convention in Kansas City, Missouri; and a 1914 bracelet medallion that reads "Come to Pittsburgh." For more information, please refer to Box 25, which contains oversized information.
    - Hemphill family tree, September 2, 1830 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Letter written from Fort Lyon to Cousin Annie, October 16, 1861 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Cousin Lizzie to Maggie, August 26, 1863 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Unknown to Cousin George, April 12, 1886 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Letter written by Cousin H.H. Anderson, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Bound News Clipping Volumes, 1898-1917; IX.
  This series consists of 29 bound volumes of newspaper clippings. These clippings may have come from a subscription service and many of the books have Mary O'Hara Darlington's name handwritten inside the front cover. The Darlingtons, particularly Mary O'Hara Darlington, may have pasted the clippings into the books. Each volume collects articles on a particular topic or event from local, national and international newspapers and magazines. However, each volume contains some clippings that do not seem to be directly related to the topic of the volume. Some volumes have a partial handwritten index. Many clippings do not contain source or date information. The title, number and dates listed below reflect the original handwritten inscriptions on the spine of each volume.
  - The War between the United States and Spain, Vol. I, 1898 (Box 30, Volume 11)
  - The War between the United States and Spain, Vol. II (Box 30, Volume 12)
  - The War between the United States and Spain, Vol. III, 1898 (Box 30, Volume 13)
  - The War between the United States and Spain, Vol. IV, 1898 (Box 30, Volume 14)
  - The War between the United States and Spain, Vol. V / The War in the Philippines, Vol. I, 1898-1899 (Box 30, Volume 14a)
  - The War between the United States and Spain Supplement, 1898 (Box 30, Volume 15)
  - The War in the Philippines / Events after the War between the United States and Spain, Vol. II, 1899 (Box 30, Volume 16)
  - The War in the Philippines / Events after the War between the United States and Spain, Vol. III, 1900 (Box 30, Volume 17)
  - The War in the Philippines / Events after the War between the United States and Spain, Vol. IV, 1900-1901 (Box 30, Volume 18)
  - The War in the Philippines / Affairs in Cuba and Puerto Rico, Vol. V, 1901-1902, 1906 (Box 30, Volume 18a)
  - The Philippines [and] Puerto Rico, Vol. IV, 1906-1907 (Box 30, Volume 19)
  - The Philippines, Mexico [and] Cuba, 1914-1916 (Box 30, Volume 20)
  - The War in China, Vol. I, 1900 (Box 30, Volume 21)
  - The War in China, Vol. II, 1900-1901 (Box 30, Volume 22)
  - The War in South Africa, 1899-1902, 1906 (Box 30, Volume 23)
  - Wars between Turkey and Italy and Italy and the Balkan States and Turkey, 1912-1913 (Box 10, Volume 24)
  - The Great War of 1914, September-October 1914 (Box 10, Volume 25)
  - The Great War of 1914, November-December 1914, January 1915 (Box 10, Volume 26)
  - Events of Interest: Earthquakes and Volcanoes, 1901-1906 (Box 10, Volume 27)
  - Events of Interest: Earthquakes and Volcanoes, 1906-1907 (Box 10, Volume 28)
  - Events of Interest: North and South Pole, 1909-1913 (Box 10, Volume 29)
  - Events of Interest, 1898-1907 (Box 10, Volume 30)
  - Events of Interest, 1907-1910 (Box 10, Volume 31)
  - Events of Interest, undated (Box 10, Volume 32)
  - Events of Interest: Biography, 1910-1913 (Box 10, Volume 33)
  - Events of Interest: Biography, 1914-1917 (Box 10, Volume 34)
  - Events of Interest: Biography, undated (Box 10, Volume 35)
  - Events of Interest: War between Russia and Japan, 1904-1906 (Box 10, Volume 36)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 10, Volume 37)
- Scrapbooks, ca. 1850-1950; X.
  The Darlington family scrapbooks consist of 11 bound volumes documenting local and national events. The items have been retained in their original arrangement, but lack any discernable order. Dated clippings range from late nineteenth to early twentieth centuries. The majority of the items in the books are newspaper clippings from local and national newspapers and detail people, places, and items of interest in and around Pittsburgh, with a number of clippings about the Darlingtons themselves. Most are undated, though some have printed or handwritten dates on them, and lack the name of the publication. Programs, sheet music, maps, sketches appearing in newspapers, magazine clippings, obituaries, and clippings concerning areas other than Pennsylvania are also included in the scrapbooks.
  Some of the books contain alphabetized indexes of the clippings and others handwritten indexes affixed to or written on the inside covers of the scrapbooks. One book contains the name of the book's binder, the date it was bound, and the cost of binding, while another has the name Mary O'Hara Darlington inscribed on the inside of the front cover.
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1850s-1880s (Box 6a, Volume 38)
    Inside cover signed by William M. Darlington. Contains lithographs and engravings of noted individuals. Only first half of scrapbook is complete.
  - Scrapbook, 1891-1898 (Box 6a, Volume 39)
    Inside cover signed by Mary O'Hara Darlington, Guyasuta. Pages cut from album (disbound). Contains newsclippings of events of interest, 1891-1898 (inc. index).
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1907-1912 (Box 6a, Volume 40)
    Mostly clippings pertaining to the subject of art and Pittsburgh Artists Association; likely assembled and kept by Mary Darlington.
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1860s-1880s (Box 6a, Volume 41)
    Mostly clippings pertaining to the history of Pittsburgh, likely created by William Darlington.
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1870s-1880s (Box 7a, Volume 42)
    Noted as Vol. 2 in the inside cover; likely created by William Darlington.
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1880-1920s (Box 7a, Volume 43)
    Darlington family scrapbook containing wealth of information about family members and Guyasuta.
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1820s-1870s (Box 8a, Volume 55)
    Newsclippings documenting Pittsburgh history and ninteenth century obituaries and other matters. Index in back.
  - Scrapbook (Box 8a, Volume 56)
    Engravings and prints with index; most likely created by O'Hara Darlington.
  - Scrapbook, 1879-1922 (Box 8a, Volume 57)
    Inside cover inscribed: Minnie O'Hara Darlington, Christmas 1879, Guyasuta. Contains newsclips.
  - Scrapbook (Box 9a, Volume 58)
    Pittsburgh and U.S. biographies and history newsclippings.
  - Scrapbook (Box 9a, Volume 59)
    Newsclippings of Pittsburgh and Virginia families and many other matters with index.
- Photographs, 1881-1882, 1885-1888; XI.
  This series contains 155 photographs in five albums taken by Edith Dennison Darlington Ammon and her brother, O'Hara Darlington, from 1885 through 1888. The photographs document family, friends, leisure activities, and the artistic approach to photography shared by Edith and O'Hara. Most of the photographs are taken in and around the family home, Guyasuta, and the surrounding area. The fifth album in this collection contains photographs from the Pittsburgh Amateur Photographers' Society, a social club founded in 1885 in which Edith and O'Hara actively participated. All the photo albums are scanned and available online.
  The series also comprises two scrapbooks containing photographs and other memorabilia documenting the Darlington family trip to Constantinople, Greece, Italy and Egypt in 1881-1882.
  - Photo Albums, 1885-1888 (Box 7a, Volume 44-48)
  - Darlington Family Trip, Volume 1, 1881-1882 (Box 10a, Volume 60)
    Photographs and other memorabilia from Constantinople, Greece, Italy, etc.
  - Darlington Family Trip, Volume 2, 1882 (Box 10a, Volume 61)
    Photographs and other memorabilia from Egypt.
- Mary Carson Darlington Artwork, 1867-1925; XII.
  This series contains 116 pieces of artwork created by Mary Carson Darlington between 1867 and her death in 1925. They contain landscapes and portraits mainly in watercolor. The large paintings have been matted and stored separately from the family papers.
  - Oversize Artwork, Artwork in boxes 20-24 are located in Flat Files 14-7 through 14-10 (Oversize 11)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 12)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 13)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 14)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 15)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 16)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 17)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 18)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 19)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 20)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 21)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 22)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 23)
  - Oversize Artwork (Oversize 24)
- Oversize Materials, 1785-1899; XIII.
  This series contains land deeds, survey information, and indentures held by the Darlington Family, dating from 1785 to 1899. Also included in this series are oversized documents relating to the collection, including: a diploma, medals, buttons, photos, deeds, and land surveys. The materials in this series relate to areas of collection interests to the Darlington family and owned by the Darlington family. These files are too large to be filed within the preceding manuscript series for family members, and contains information about them, their research interests, education, and land holdings.
  - O'Hara and Richardson, Survey Information, October 17, 1785 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Mary C. Darlington, Land Warrant, October 17, 1785 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - William Bamer, Deed, January 18, 1793 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Robert Campbell, Deed, October 1817 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin Darlington, Deed, November 29, 1822 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - James Rope, Indenture, 1829 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Richardson, Patent (copy), December 17, 1839 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - William Darlington, Deed, July 19, 1850 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Mary O'Hara and Mary Darlington, May 28, 1857 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - William and Mary Darlington, March, 23, 1887 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Mary Darlington, Deed, May, 8, 1890 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - O'Hara Darlington, Taxes, January 15, 1893 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Inventory of Darlington Family Lot Surveys, undated (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Sale of Land, undated (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - David Stule, Land Survey Information, undated (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Sam Jones, Deed, January 4, 1806 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - William Mann, Indenture, October 7, 1811 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Alex Young and Fredrick Myers, Indenture, May 1812 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Act to erect a Bridge by Governor, August 13, 1845 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Hearman Demery, William Crogan, James Roph, and Mary O'Hara to James, Deed, January 26, 1846 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - John White and Mary O'Hara, Indenture, April 1, 1848 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Mary O'Hara to John White, Deed, April 22, 1848 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - James O'Hara, Indenture, April 5, 1849 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - James O'Hara, Indenture, April 5, 1849 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - John Whiteknife and Mary O'Hara, Deed, April 14, 1851 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Charles Shirk, Deed, May 3, 1856 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - William Boyle, William Darlington, and Mary O'Hara, Deed, September 16, 1856 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - William Darlington and William Johnson, Indenture, November 14, 1859 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Mary Darlington, Deed, March 21, 1866 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Mary Darlington, Deed, March 21, 1866 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Mary Darlington, Deed, March 21, 1866 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Mary Darlington, Deed, March 21, 1866 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - William and Mary Darlington, Deed, November 4, 1884 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Mary Darlington, Deed, August 23, 1899 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - William Trent's Account of Proceedings with Six Nations of Indians and Allies, November 17, 1753 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - William Darlington, Certificate of Acceptance into the Bar, November 20, 1837 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - William Darlington, Certificate of Acceptance to the Academy of Natural Sciences, November 24, 1868 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - O'Hara Darlington, Yale Diploma, 1871 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - William Darlington, Survey of Darlington Land on Loyalhanna Creek, May 9, 1879 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Buttons and Badge Memorabilia, 1900-1914 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - O'Hara Darlington, Certificate of Membership in Historical Society of Pennsylvania, undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Four Unlabeled Photographs, undated (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Design notes for library bookcases, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Deed to the Estate of Jane McCullough, undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Portrait of William M. Darlington, undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Three Paintings of Natural Scenes, undated (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Floor plan of Guyasuta, undated (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Photos of the Darlington Property at Marshall Avenue and Brighton Road, undated (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Darlington Index List, undated (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Plan Book, ca. 1860-1884 (Box 29)
    Contains lot and block information (some drawn by hand) for Pittsburgh and surrounding area; not necessarily property owned by Darlington family, but collected for historic reasons.